Register of the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
Hoover Institution Archives
Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
1903-1990
XX843
Hoover Institution Archives
1011 microfilm reels (151.7 linear feet)
Relates to political conditions in the Soviet Union from 1917 to 1991. Filmed from finding aids and holdings dating from 1903 to 1991 of the Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv noveisheĭ istorii.
Kommunisticheskai͡a partii͡a Sovetskogo Soi͡uza.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Original Materials
The original documents are located in three Russian archives:
-Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv noveisheĭ istorii - RGANI)
-Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv sot͡sial'no-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
and
-State Archives of the Russian Federation (Gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv Rossiĭskoĭ Federat͡sii - GARF).
Related Materials
Portions or the entirety of the microfilm collection may be found at the following institutions in addition to the Hoover Institution: The Library of Congress, Grinnell College, Harvard University, John Hopkins University, University of North Carolina Chapel Hill, Ohio University, University of Washington, University of Melbourne Australia, Glasgow University United Kingdom, Bavarian State University, Germany, and Hokkaido University, Japan.
The microfilms containing only the Russian language opisi or finding aids may be found at the following institutions: University of Illinois, Indiana University, Columbia University, and New York University.
Scope and Content of the Microfilm Collection
This collection concerns political conditions in the Soviet Union from 1917 to 1991. The documents come from three Russian archives. Material was selected for microfilming based on two criteria: (1) records of the highest policy-making units of the Communist Party were the priority; and (2) record series were filmed in their entirety, rather than selecting only particular files or documents (except for some of the Gulag material in GARF) Fond R-9414).
To locate material in the collection, it helps to know that archival documents in the former Soviet Union, and later in the Russian Federation, are arranged in record groups according to the institution that issued or received them. These major groups, which sometimes include thousands of documents, are called in Russian fond (plural fondy). Within each fond the documents are generally divided into smaller groups called opisi (singular opis). opisi are generally organized according to the internal structure of the corresponding institution, but sometimes opisi consist of documents relating to one subject. The Russian word opis has two meanings: (1) a series of documents; and (2) a finding aid. Each opis "series of documents" is provided with a descriptive opis "finding aid." Each opis "series of documents" is further organized into files called dela (singular delo) that contain the documents.
Out of a total of 11,818 microfilm reels, 11,349 reels contain documents and 469 contain finding aids to the fondy available at the Hoover Institution, as well as to some fondy available only in Russia. Each reel of microfilm contains approximately 850 pages, or frames.
The microfilm reel numbers consist of two parts separated by a period, for example 3.427. The first numerical segment is a 1, 2, or 3, identifying the Russian archive source; 1 is RGANI, 2 is RGASPI, and 3 is GARF. The second segment, which is sequentially numbered starting with 1, represents a specific microfilm reel number for that Russian archive.
Scope and Content of the RGANI Records
Materials described in this document are from the Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv noveisheĭ istorii - RGANI).
Finding Aids to Fondy 4, 5, 6, 8, and 89 at RGANI (15 reels). These Russian-language finding aids were created by RGANI to describe documents in fondy 4-6, 8, and 89. Only the documents in fondy 6 ( opisi 1-6) and 89 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives.
The documents of Fond 6 include materials from the Party Control Commission of the TsK VKP(b), 1934-1952; the Party Control Committee of the TsK KPSS, 1952-1962; and the Party Commission of the TsK KPSS, 1962-1966.
The records of Fond 89, Communist Party of the Soviet Union on Trial records, 1918-1992, consist of documents submitted to the Constitutional Court of the Russian Federation for the trial of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union.
Arrangement
The collection is organized by the name of the Russian archive that holds the original materials. There are three finding aids for the collection, one for each one of the Russian Archives:
-Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv noveisheĭ istorii - RGANI)
-Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv sot͡sial'no-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
and
-State Archives of the Russian Federation (Gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv Rossiĭskoĭ Federat͡sii - GARF).
Within Russian institutional archive, the materials are organized into two groups: (1) fondy (record groups consisting of documents); and (2) finding aids that describe each fondy. Fondy are usually subdivided into opisi (series of documents); the number of opisi in each fondy varies.
Glossary
This glossary defines acronyms and names for all three organizations of the microfilming project: the Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI), the Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI), and the State Archives of the Russian Federation (Gosudarstvennyi arkhiv Rossiiskoi Federatsii - GARF).
ASSR
Avtonomnaia Sovetskaia sotsialisticheskaia respublika
BUND
The General Jewish Workers' Union in Lithuania, Poland, and Russia
Gospolitizdat
Gosudarstvennoe izdatelstvo politichesko literatury
GUITK
Glavnoe upravlenie ispravitel'no-trudovykh kolonii
Gulag
Glavnoe upravlenie ispravitel'no-trudovykh lagerei
GUMZ
Glavnoe upravlenie mest zakliucheniia
IKKI
Ispolnitelnyi komitet Kommunisticheskogo Internatsionala
IMEL
Institut Marksa-Engelsa-Lenina
Komsomol
Kommunisticheskii soiuz molodezhi
KPSS
Kommunisticheskaia partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza
Krymizdat
Krymskoe izdatelstvo
Lenizdat
Leningradskoe izdatelstvo
Malyi Sovnarkom
Malyi sovet narodnykh komissarov
MOPR
Mezhdunarodnaia organizatsiia pomoshchi bortsam revoliutsii
MVD
Ministerstvo vnutrennikh del
NKGB
Narodnyi Commissariat gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti
NKID
Narodnyi kommisariat inostrannykh del
NKPS
Narodnyi kommisariat putei soobshcheniia
NKVD
Narodnyi kommisariat vnutrennikh del
OGIZ
Obiedinennoe gosudarstvennoe izdatelstvo
OGPU
Obiedinennoe gosudarstvennoe politicheskoe upravlenie
Okruzhkom
Okruzhnoi komitet [partii]
Politizdat
Izdatel'stvo politicheskoi literatury
Profintern
Krasnyi internatsional profsoiuzov
PUR RVS
Politicheskoe upravlenie revoliutsionno- voennogo soveta
RKI
Raboche-krestianskaia inspektsiia
RKP(b)
Rossiiskaia kommunisticheskaia partiia (Bolshevikov)
ROSTA
Rossiiskoe telegrafnoe agenstvo
RSDRP
Rossiiskaia Sotsial-Demokraticheskaia Rabochaiia Partiia
RSFSR
Rossiiskaia Sovetskaia Federativnaia Sotsialisticheskaia Respublika
RVSR
Revoliutsionno-voennyi sovet respubliki
SNK or Sovnarkom
Sovet narodnykh kommisarov
SSR
Sovetskaia sotsialisticheskaia respublica
STO
Sovet truda i oborony
Tsentrosoiuz
Tsentralnyi soiuz kooperativnykh obshchestv
TsIK
Tsentral'nyi ispolnitel'nyi komitet
TsK
Tsentralnyi Komitet
TsKK
Tsentralnaia kontrolnaia komissiia
TSU
Tsentralnoe statisticheskoe upravlenie
VChK
Vserossiiskaia chrezvychainaia komissiia
VKP(b)
Vsesoiuznaia kommunisticheskaia partiia (Bolshevikov)
VLKSM
Vsesoiuznyi Leninskii Kommunisticheskii Soiuz molodezhi
VSNKh
Vysshii Sovet Narodnogo Khoziaistva
VTsIK
Vserossiiskii tsentral'nyi ispolnitel'nyi komitet
VUChK
Vseukrainskaia chrezvychainaia komissiia
USSR
Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
Soviet Union--History.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; Communism--Soviet Union.
Collection Contents
- Finding Aids to Fondy 4, 5, 6, 8, and 89 at RGANI, 15 reels (Reel 1.1-1.14, 1.988)
  These Russian-language finding aids were created by RGANI to describe documents in fondy 4-6, 8, and 89. Only the documents in fondy 6 and 89 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives. The microfilm reel list is:
  Fond 4, opisi 9, 15-20, 22-23 on reel 1.1
  Fond 4, opisi 24, 26 on reel 1.2
  Fond 5, opisi 11, 14-18, 20-22 on reel 1.3
  Fond 5, opisi 23-34 on reel 1.4
  Fond 5, opisi 35-45 on reel 1.5
  Fond 5, opisi 46-50, 54-55 on reel 1.6
  Fond 5, opisi 58-62 on reel 1.7
  Fond 5, opisi 63-64, 66-67 on reel 1.8
  Fond 5, opisi 68-89, 73 on reel 1.9
  Fond 5, opisi 73-77 on reel 1.10
  Fond 5, opis 84 on reel 1.11
  Fond 6, opisi 1-4 on reel 1.12
  Fond 6, opisi 5-9 on reel 1.13
  Fond 8, opisi 1-4, 6-15 on reel 1.14
  Fond 89, opisi 1-76 on reel 1.988.
- Fond 2, Opisi 1, 3, and 5, Plenumy T͡Sentralʹnogo Komiteta Kommunisticheskoĭ partii Sovetskogo Soi͡uza, 1941-1990
  Available at the Green Library at Stanford.
- Fond 5, Opis 28, Otdel T͡SK KPSS po svi͡azi͡am s inostrannymi kompartii͡ami (Mezhdunarodnyĭ otdel T͡SK KPSS), 1953-1957
- Fond 5, Opis 30, The General Department of the Central Committee [microform] = Obshchiĭ otdel T͡SK KPSS, 1953-1966
- Fond 6, The Party Control Commission of the TsK VKP(b), 1934-1952, the Party Control Committee of the TsK KPSS, 1952-1962, the Party Commission of the TsK KPSS, 1962-1966
  Scope Note
  This finding aid has been prepared for 913 microfilm reels of opisi 1-6 of Fond 6. They contain 10,035 files of documents relating to the activities of the party Control Commission/Committee, 1934-1966.
  The Central Control Commission was reorganized into the Party Control Commission (KPK) of the TsK VKP(b) in February 1934 at the XVII Party Congress. The Party Control Commission was established to work between party congresses. At congresses the structure and responsibilities of the Commission were defined. The Party Control Commission of the XVII Congress had control over the fulfillment of decisions of the TsK VKP(b) and of the Party and brought to account those guilty of violations of party discipline and party ethics.
  The work of the Commission was organized as follows:
  1. KPK Plenum
  2. KPK Bureau
  3. KPK Secretariat
  4. KPK Party Collegium
  5. KPK teams for various branches of Soviet economic and cultural development
  6. KPK representatives to republics, krais, and oblasts
  The plenum was the KPK governing organ until 1936; from 1936 the KPK Bureau, whose members were to be approved by the TsK VKP(b), headed the KPK.
  The KPK Collegium reviewed complaints filed against decisions of local party organs. To facilitate the resolution of complaints, a three-member party body (troĭka) was appointed to review them. Sometimes troĭka members went to the locality where those who filed the complaint lived.
  The KPK Secretariat managed the work of administrative personnel.
  Fifteen teams within the KPK controlled the activities of people's commissariats and departments.
  The KPK appointed representatives to the republics, krais and oblasts to control the fulfillment of party decisions by local party, economic, and Soviet organizations. Attached to each KPK Representative was a three-member party body (troĭka) approved by the KPK. The troĭka investigated cases relating to violations of party discipline and party ethics. The troĭka's decisions had to be approved by a KPK representative in the locality. Complaints against the troĭka's decision could be filed to the KPK of the TsK VKP(b).
  Documents in opisi 1-6 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Institution Archives. Russian-language finding aids available on microfilm are: Opisi 1-4 on microfilm reel number 1.12; Opisi 5-9 on reel number 1.13.
  - Opis 1, Minutes of the Party Control Commission of the TsK VKP(b), 1934-1939; 412 reels (Reel 1.15-1.173)
    Opis 1 includes minutes of KPK Plenums, the KPK Bureau, the KPK Party Collegium, and party troĭkas of the TsK VKP(b), KPK and party collegiums and party troĭkas in the republics, krais, and oblasts, as well as troĭkas of the KPK Party Collegium that investigated complaints of those expelled from the party during the review of party documents that took place from February 1934 through March 1939 (912 files). Some protocols for the years 1934-1939 were left in the archives building in 1941 during the evacuation and presumably were destroyed by paramilitary guards. Minutes No. 1-275 for the years 1938-1939 were restored in 1967-1970 using excerpts from the minutes that were preserved by the TsK KPSS Sector of Unified Party Member Identification Cards of the TsK KPSS and in personal files. It is believed that not all items on the troĭkas' agendas could be restored in full.
    The minutes are arranged chronologically. Minutes relating to each Plenum are arranged by number within the following six groups:
    1. Minutes and verbatim records of KPK Plenums
    2. Minutes of the KPK Bureau
    3. Minutes of the KPK Party Collegium
    4. Minutes of the party troĭka of the KPK Party Collegium
    5. Minutes of the party troĭkas of the KPK Party Collegium and of KPK party collegiums in republics, krais, and oblasts
    6. Minutes of the Party Collegium and party troĭkas of the KPK Party Collegium for review of complaints of party members expelled from the party during the documents review
    Materials of plenums include minutes and verbatim records, draft resolutions, notes by a main speaker at the Plenum, and other documents. Three versions of verbatim records have been preserved: the author's version, an edited typescript, and a printed copy. Meeting minute numbers and plenum minute numbers are the same.
    Minutes of the KPK Bureau were approved by the TsK VKP(b) Organizational Bureau. Minutes of the KPK Bureau have been preserved in two versions: the original and an identical copy. Each file includes a minute and supplementary material to this meeting.
    Documents are further arranged in a similar way: the original, a resolution, an attachment to the resolution, supplementary material, and a resolution adopted without a meeting, by interviewing Bureau members.
    Some protocols contain resolutions adopted by interviewing Bureau members and supplementary materials. Agenda items of the KPK Bureau marked as "Special Folder" are listed on the cover of a corresponding file.
    Resolutions adopted at the joint meetings of the KPK of the TsK VKP(b) and the Soviet Control Commission under the USSR Sovnarkom were written personally by V. Kuibyshev, head of the Soviet Control Commission and of the State Planning Committee (Gosplan). Separate files numbered 1-52 contain KPK Bureau decisions for May - October 1936 relating to plans for revision of TsK VKP(b) and USSR Sovnarkom resolutions and materials removed from consideration at the KPK Bureau meetings.
    Minutes of the KPK Party Collegium containing items adopted by interviewing Bureau members are placed in files after the main minutes of the KPK Party Collegium.
    Minutes of the troĭkas of the KPK Party Collegium were approved by the Party Collegium Secretary, and minutes reviewing complaints directed to the XVII Congress, by the KPK Bureau.
    - Minutes and verbatim records of the KPK Plenums, 1934-1936 (Opis 1, Reel 1.15-1.17)
      - Minutes nos. 1 and 2 of the meeting of the First Plenum of the Party Control Commission (KPK) of the TsK VKP(b) of 10 and 19 February 1934 (original); minutes No. 2 (facsimile copy), and resolutions adopted (originals), with related materials, including agenda, list of participants, and reports of the Second Plenum of the KPK of 26-28 June 1934; verbatim records of the Second KPK Plenum regarding reports of KPK representatives (June 26), implementation of decisions of the XII Congress of the VKP(b) on revision of work of people's commissariats (author's and corrected copies); verbatim record of the Second Plenum of the Party Control Commission (KPK) of the TsK VKP(b) of 27-28 July 1934 regarding fishing season, execution of resolutions of the XII Party Congress, work of trade unions on "control work," light cavalry, and influence of the press on the work of trade unions in "control work,", 1934 June 17-28 (Opis 1, Reel 1.15, File 1-9)
      - Resolutions of the 3rd Plenum of the Commission for Party Control: of 15 December 1934 regarding approval of M. F. Shkiriatov as the Second Deputy of the KPK Chair (protocol No. 3, paragraph 1c); of 1 April 1935 regarding increase in number of members of the Bureau of the Party Control Commission of the TsK VKP(b); resolution of the Plenum of the Party Control Commission of the TsK VKP(b) of 7-9 March 1936 (author's copy and a typed copy after author's corrections); verbatim records of the 3rd Plenum of the KPK of the TsK VKP(b): of 7 and 8 March 1936 regarding work of KPK representatives at the TsK VKP(b); of 9-10 March 1936 regarding work of Party Collegium of the KPK and rules for imposing party punishment on VKP(b) members and candidate members (author's copy and a copy typed after author's corrections), 1934 December 15 - 1936 March 10 (Opis 1, Reel 1.16, File 9-18)
      - Verbatim records of the 3rd Plenum of the KPK of the TsK VKP(b) (morning and evening meetings of 10 March 1936; copy typed after author's corrections); verbatim record of the 3rd Plenum of the KPK of 7-10 March 1936 regarding work of KPK representatives at the TsK VKP(b) (print from typesetting) and work of the KPK Party Collegium and rules for imposing party punishment on VKP(b) members and candidate members (a copy typed after author's corrections and a print from typesetting), 1936 March 7-10 (Opis 1, Reel 1.17, File 18-19)
    - Minutes of the KPK Bureau with related materials, 1934-1939 (Opis 1, Reel 1.17-1.29)
      - Minutes of the Bureau of the KPK of the TsK VKP(b) nos. 2-11 of 21 and 27 February; of 8, 17, and 31 March; of 8, 17, and 27 April; and of 5 and 10 May 1934, with related materials. Originals, 1934 February 21 - May 10 (Opis 1, Reel 1.17, File 20-29)
      - Minutes of the Bureau of the KPK of the TsK VKP(b) no. 12 of 1 June 1934, no. 13 of 11, 13, and 14 June 1934; no. 14 of 10 July 1934; no. 15 of 2 August (paragraphs 1s-15s and 1g-41g), and no. 16 of 16 August 1934, with related materials; minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 17 of 20 August - 9 September 1934 containing resolutions adopted by votes cast in questionnaires (oprosnye postanovleniia) with related materials. Originals, 1934 May 11 - September 9 (Opis 1, Reel 1.18, File 30-36)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 18 of 25 September 1934; no. 19 of 16 October 1934; no. 20 of 1 November 1934; and no. 21 of 19 November 1935, with related materials; minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 22 of 21 November - 29 December containing resolutions adopted by votes cast in questionnaires (oprosnye postanovleniia) with related materials; minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 23 of 13 February 1935 (paragraphs 1s-16s), with related materials. Originals, 1934 September 25 - 1935 February 13 (Opis 1, Reel 1.19, File 37-42)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 23 of 13 February 1935 (paragraphs 1g-71g), no. 24 of 11 March 1935 (paragraphs 1s-24s and 1g-44g), with related materials; minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 25 of 8 April 1935, with related materials. Originals, 1935 January 3 - April 8 (Opis 1, Reel 1.20, File 43-47)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 26 of 23 May 1935 (paragraphs 1s-13s and 1g-13g); minutes no. 27 of 26 May - 16 July 1935 (paragraphs 1g-93g) containing resolutions adopted by votes cast in questionnaires (oprosnye postanovleniia), with related materials; minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 28 of 23 August 1935 (paragraphs 1s-15s and 1g-51g), with related materials. Originals, 1935 May 23 - August 23 (Opis 1, Reel 1.21, File 48-53)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 29 of 11 October 1935; no. 30 of 28 October 1935; no. 31 of 21 November 1935; and no. 32 of 2 February 1936 (paragraphs 1s-18s and 1g-60g); with related materials. Originals, 1935 October 11 - 1936 February 2 (Opis 1, Reel 1.22, File 54-58)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 33 of 29 February - 3 March 1936; no. 34 of 16 March 1936; no. 35 of 9 April 1936; no. 36 of 21 April 1936; and no. 37 of 17 May 1936, with related materials. Originals, 1936 February 7 - May 17 (Opis 1, Reel 1.23, File 59-63)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 38 of 9-10 July 1936 (paragraphs 1s-16s and 1g-57g); and no. 39 of 29 October 1936 (paragraphs 1s-12s and 1g-155g), with related materials. Originals, 1936 May 23 - October 29 (Opis 1, Reel 1.24, File 64-67)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 40 of 1 December 1936; no. 41 of 14 January 1937, no. 42 of 7 March 1937, no. 43 of 7 March 1937; and no. 44 of 20 April 1937 (paragraphs 1s - 17 s), with related materials. Originals, 1936 November 5 - 1937 April 20 (Opis 1, Reel 1.25, File 68-72)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 44 (paragraphs 1g-35g) of 20 April 1937, with related materials; no. 45 of 25 April - 20 June 1937; no. 46 of 22 June - 31 July; and no. 47 of 4 August - 16 October 1937 containing resolutions adopted by votes cast in questionnaires (oprosnye postanovleniia), with related materials. Originals, 1937 March 17 - October 16 (Opis 1, Reel 1.26, File 73-76)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 48 of 28 October; and no. 49 of 17 November 1937, with related materials (originals); minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 50 of 19 November 1937 - 29 January 1938 containing resolutions adopted by votes cast in questionnaires (oprosnye postanovleniia) with related materials (originals); minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 51 of 22 February 1938; no. 52 of 2 March 1938; and no. 53 of 27 March 1938, with related materials. Originals, 1937 October 17 - 1938 March 27 (Opis 1, Reel 1.27, File 77-82)
      - Minutes of the KPK Bureau of the TsK VKP(b) no. 54 of 4 July 1938; no. 55 of 28 July 1938; no. 56 of 5 August 1938; no. 57 of 14 September 1938, no. 58 of 21-23 October 1938; nos. 59-60 of 3 January 1939; and no. 60 of 26 January 1939, with related materials. Originals, 1938 March 29 - 1939 January 26 (Opis 1, Reel 1.28, File 83-89)